A Guide to the Edwin Houston Harman Letters, 1860-1864
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Edwin Houston Harman Letters, 1860-1864
Library of Virginia
27935
32 leaves, negative photostats
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Lent for copying by Harriet Louisa Tynes, 1009 Carolina Street, Greensboro, North Carolina, 23 March 1972.
Biographical Information
Edwin Houston Harman was born 13 February 1835 in Tazewell County, Virginia, to Erastus Granger Harman (1804-1852) and Sallie Bane Harman (1811-1897). Harman attended Emory and Henry College. When the Civil War began, Harman enlisted at Wytheville, Virginia, 29 May 1861, and became captain of Company H, 45th Virginia Infantry. He was promoted to lieutenant colonel 14 May 1862. Harman was mortally wounded 9 May 1864 at the battle of Cloyd's Mountain, dying two days later 11 May 1864. Harman married Jennie King (1838-1910) of Pulaski County, Virginia, 2 April 1861 and they had two children. Harman was buried in Thornspring Cemetery in Pulaski County.
Scope and Content
Letters, 1860-1864, from Edwin Houston Harman (1835-1864) of Tazewell County, Virginia, to his cousin Harriet Louisa Fudge (1842-1922) of Tazewell County, discussing life in Tazewell County; his wife, Jennie, and their two boys; Harriett's brother Charlie; and other family and personal news. Harman also provides news about his regiment, the 45th Virginia Infantry, describing camp life and some of the fighting the regiment was involved in.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Achilles J. Tynes Letters, 1864-1951 (LVA accession 27936)
Historic Crab Orchard Museum papers, [1598?]-1922 (LVA accession 34648)
Contents List
- Correspondence, 1860-1864 (Folder 1)
  - Letter, 17 June 1860, from Edwin H. Harman, Tazewell County, Virginia, to his cousin Hat [Harriett Louisa Fudge] concerning his affections for Miss K. [possibly Jennie King whom he later married] and other news., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, January 1861, from Edwin H. Harman, Tazewell County, to his cousin Hat discussing his fiancee and her love life along with personal news including the possibility of war and enlistment., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 13 December 1861, from Edwin H. Harman, in camp, to cousin Hat concerning her brother Charlie coming home on furlough and also about his wife Jennie. Harman also mentions his health., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 23 March 1862, from Edwin H. Harman to cousin Hat concerning the 45th Virginia and her brother. He comments on the military strategy being pursued in southwestern Virginia. Harman mentions his wife and child., 4 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 25 May 1862, from Edwin H. Harman to cousin Hat describing a fight between Confederate and Union forces at Lewistown, (West) Virginia and his part in the battle., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 4 January 1863, from Edwin H. Harman to cousin Hat concerning his command of the 45th Virginia, a disagreement with her brother, and other news from camp, including his health., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 7 April 1863, from Edwin H. Harman to cousin Hat detailing a quick trip he made to his home and other personal news. He offers some general comments on the war., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Correspondence, 1860-1864 (Folder 2)
  - Letter, 28 June 1863, from Edwin H. Harman to cousin Hat discussing camp life and personal news. Harman laments that his regiment is not seeing much action while there is plenty of fighting elsewhere., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 2 September 1863, from Edwin H. Harman to cousin Hat discussing a fight that they had with Union troops., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 11 November 1863, from Edwin H. Harman to cousin Hat stating that Confederate cavalry, including the 8th Virginia, has captured guns, horses, and 800 prisoners. Harman does not like the way the war progresses in southwestern Virginia and in Tennessee., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 13 January 1864, from Edwin H. Harman to cousin Hat describing a trip home to his wife and now two children. He mentions Hat's pending marriage and asks when her brother Charlie will be returning to the regiment., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, 16 March 1864, from Edwin H. Harman to cousin Hat discussing her marriage and asking her to write him. Harman mentions his family. He notes that the regiment has moved., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
  - Letter, n.d., from Edwin H. Harman to cousin Hat., 2 leaves, fragments, negative photostats.
  - Letter, n.d., from Edwin H. Harman to cousin Hat concerning his and Charlie's love lives., 2 leaves, incomplete, negative photostats.
  - Letter, n.d. [1862?], from Edwin H. Harman to cousin Hat containing family and personal news. He also comments on his regiment., 2 leaves, negative photostats.